<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0" xml:id="Cook-Lydgate-24-Young-Ladies-Headnote-tei">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt><title>Introduction to A Mirror for Young Ladies at their Toilet</title><author>Cook, Megan L.</author><author>Strakhov, Elizaveta</author><sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
 <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
 <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
 <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
 <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder><respStmt><persName>Conklin, Ashley R.</persName><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-08">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-08">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-08">Entered corrections for print edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName><resp from="2023-02" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName><resp from="2024-02" to="2024-02">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Norris, James</persName><resp from="2024-03" to="2024-05">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Price, Eleanor</persName><resp from="2024-03" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2023-11" to="2023-11">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Entered corrections for print edition</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Formatted for print edition</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Formatted for XML export</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Yee, Pamela M.</persName><resp from="2018-07" to="2024-01">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp>Collated and entered corrections</resp><resp from="2023-11" to="2023-11">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Encoded in TEI in 2024</edition>
 </editionStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
 <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <availability status="restricted">
 <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
 </availability>
    <date/>
 </publicationStmt><seriesStmt>
 <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title><respStmt><persName>Ralph Arbelo</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Mead Bowen</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Katherine Briant</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Theresa Coletti</persName><orgName>University of Maryland</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Ashley R. Conklin</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Rita Copeland</persName><orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Steffi Delcourt</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Joe Easterly</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Susanna Fein</persName><orgName>Kent State University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Sue Gleason</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>David A. Lawton</persName><orgName>Washington University in St. Louis</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Michael Livingston</persName><orgName>The Citadel</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Alan Lupack</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Andrea Noto</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Katie Papas</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Section Supervisor, The Robbins Library, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Russell A. Peck</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Eve Salisbury</persName><orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Nathan Sarr</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName><orgName>University of Florida</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Lynn Staley</persName><orgName>Colgate University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName><orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Pamela M. Yee</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt></seriesStmt>    
 <sourceDesc>
 <biblStruct>
 <monogr><author>Lydgate, John</author><author>Unknown</author><editor>Cook, Megan L.</editor><editor>Strakhov, Elizaveta</editor><editor role="translator">Strakhov, Elizaveta</editor><title>John Lydgate's Dance of Death and Related Works</title><imprint>
 <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace><date>2019</date></imprint>
 </monogr>
 </biblStruct>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
  <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s), textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor, congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p><correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on Github: https://github.com/mets-editions/cook-lydgate/blob/main/cook-lydgate-export-corrections-log.docx</p>
        </correction></editorialDecl><schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
 </encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change>Encoded in HTML</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
    <text><body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><anchor xml:id="Cook-Lydgate-24-Young-Ladies-Headnote"/><div type="text">
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="1">This short lyric is extant in a single manuscript dated after 1461 to 1500 (based on its inclusion of a chronicle mentioning Edward IV: see “Detailed Record for Harley 116” in the British Library’s online manuscript catalogue), which also includes Hoccleve’s <hi rend="italic">Regiment of Princes</hi>, a frequent manuscript companion to Lydgate’s <hi rend="italic">Dance of Death</hi>.</p>
 <p style="body" n="1">The poem is an address by Death to young women who pay attention to their good looks. To underscore the transitory quality of their beauty, Death implicitly compares the young women to ephemeral creatures, whose time on earth is fleeting (“Sone shalte thu flytte . . . Shorte is thy sesoun here . . . ,” lines 4–5). In the second and third stanzas, Death’s relentlessness emerges in stark contrast to the fragile beauty evoked in the opening stanza, as Death describes his actions and attributes in increasingly violent terms: “I marke thee with my mace . . . I manace . . . my lace [snare] . . . I smyte, I sle . . . ” (lines 6–14), which we also see in the <hi rend="italic">danse macabre</hi> tradition. The use of “pray” in line 9, in address to the young women, further underscores Death as a predator or hunter stalking after defenseless animals about to be caught in his trap. In this way, articulating the familiar characterization of women as prey before a predator, the lyric evokes connotations of sexual violence, suggesting that Death here is being gendered male. The lyric goes on to exhort the young women to “awake” from their vanity and pay heed to their eternal salvation (line 15).</p>
 <p style="body" n="2">The lyric’s French rubric is noteworthy given its explicit address to a female audience. Its use of French speaks to the preponderance of Frenchlanguage conduct literature aimed at women that was composed and consumed during the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries, of which Watriquet de Couvin’s <hi rend="italic">Miroer as dames</hi> (1324), <hi rend="italic">Le Livre du Chevalier de la</hi><hi rend="italic"> Tour Landry</hi> (1371–72), and <hi rend="italic">Le Menagier de Paris</hi> (c. 1393) are prime examples. For discussions of these and other texts see, in particular, <hi rend="italic">Medieval Conduct</hi>, ed. Ashley and Clark; and Burger, <hi rend="italic">Conduct Becoming</hi>.</p>
 <p style="body" n="3">The French rubric of our English poem also points to the French cultural context of the <hi rend="italic">danse macabre</hi> tradition. As Francis Utley notes, the French rubric to this poem evokes a French poem on similar themes, which opens with the lines, “Mirez vous cy, dames et damoiselles, / Mirez vous cy et regardés ma face. / Helas! pensez, se vous estes bien belles, / Comment la mort toute beauté efface” (lines 1–4: Behold yourselves here, ladies and maidens, / Behold yourself here and look at my face. / Alas! consider, if you are very beautiful, / How death effaces all beauty) (<hi rend="italic">Crooked Rib</hi>, pp. 190–91, for full text of poem see Söderhjelm, “Le miroir des dames,” pp. 31–35, translation our own). This similar French poem features a female speaker mourning the imminent progressive decomposition of her body in a French iteration of the Signs of Death genre. It is, furthermore, found in a manuscript (Paris, Bibliothèque nationale, naf. 10032) that also contains the <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Danse</hi><hi rend="italic"> macabre des femmes</hi>, which opens with almost the same wording.</p>
 <p style="body" n="4">Our English work is further distinguished by its formal complexity. Unusually, the lyric inverts its rhyme scheme in the second stanza, thus <hi rend="italic">abbba-baaab-abbba</hi> (see further Cutler, “A Middle English Acrostic,” pp. 88–89). Through this inversion, the lyric fosters a sense of the middle stanza’s being caught by the tight framing of stanzas 1 and 3, thus formally mirroring the lyric’s claustrophobic theme of Death as a hunter seizing his prey. In keeping with the notion of catching or binding and its formal reflection within the lyric’s structure, the entire work itself is an acrostic evidently intended to spell out MORS SOLVIT OMNIA, or “death loosens all,” although the lyric’s only manuscript substitutes a “B” for the necessary “N” in OMNIA. Cutler notes that this phrase is also associated with the well-known lyric “Erthe upon Erthe,” similarly a work that treats the transitory and fleeting nature of earthly possessions (“A Middle English Acrostic,” p. 89). Thus, this lyric’s content emphasizes the capture of living creatures in the tight grip of Death, as mirrored on the metapoetic level by the lyric’s internal rhyme structure. Meanwhile, in contrast, the lyric’s superstructure of the acrostic highlights the notion of death as the ultimate release from earthly bonds.</p>
 <p style="bodysubsection">Manuscript:</p>
 <list rend="nobullets"><item style="indent1">London, British Library, MS Harley 116, fols. 128r–v</item></list>
 <p style="bodysubsection">Editions:</p>
 <list rend="nobullets"><item style="indent1">Brown, Carleton Fairchild, ed. “A Mirror for Young Ladies at their Toilet.” In <hi rend="italic">Religious </hi><hi rend="italic">Lyrics of the XVth Century</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon, 1939. P. 241.</item></list>
 <list rend="nobullets"><item style="indent1">Cutler, John L., ed. “No. 2136, A Mirror for Young Ladies at their Toilet.” In “A Middle English Acrostic.” <hi rend="italic">Modern </hi><hi rend="italic">Language Notes</hi> 70.2 (1955), 88.</item></list>
 <list rend="nobullets"><item style="indent1">Silverstein, Theodore, ed. “Cest le Myrroure pur les Iofenes Dames.” In <hi rend="italic">Medieval English Lyrics</hi>. London: Edwin Arnold Ltd., 1971. Pp. 121–22.</item></list>
 </div></body></text></TEI>
