<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0" xml:id="Cook-Lydgate-18-Three-Messengers-Enotes-tei">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt><title>Explanatory Notes to Three Messengers of Death</title><author>Cook, Megan L.</author><author>Strakhov, Elizaveta</author><sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
 <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
 <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
 <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
 <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder><respStmt><persName>Conklin, Ashley R.</persName><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-08">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-08">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-08">Entered corrections for print edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName><resp from="2023-02" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName><resp from="2024-02" to="2024-02">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-03">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Norris, James</persName><resp from="2024-03" to="2024-05">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Reviewed and suggested explanatory notes</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Price, Eleanor</persName><resp from="2024-03" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2023-11" to="2023-11">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Entered corrections for print edition</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Formatted for print edition</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Formatted for XML export</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Yee, Pamela M.</persName><resp from="2018-07" to="2024-01">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp>Collated and entered corrections</resp><resp from="2023-11" to="2023-11">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Encoded in TEI in 2024</edition>
 </editionStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
 <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <availability status="restricted">
 <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
 </availability>
    <date/>
 </publicationStmt><seriesStmt>
 <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title><respStmt><persName>Ralph Arbelo</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Mead Bowen</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Katherine Briant</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Theresa Coletti</persName><orgName>University of Maryland</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Ashley R. Conklin</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Rita Copeland</persName><orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Steffi Delcourt</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Joe Easterly</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Susanna Fein</persName><orgName>Kent State University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Sue Gleason</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>David A. Lawton</persName><orgName>Washington University in St. Louis</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Michael Livingston</persName><orgName>The Citadel</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Alan Lupack</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Andrea Noto</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Katie Papas</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Section Supervisor, The Robbins Library, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Russell A. Peck</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Eve Salisbury</persName><orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Nathan Sarr</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName><orgName>University of Florida</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Lynn Staley</persName><orgName>Colgate University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName><orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Pamela M. Yee</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt></seriesStmt>    
 <sourceDesc>
 <biblStruct>
 <monogr><author>Lydgate, John</author><author>Unknown</author><editor>Cook, Megan L.</editor><editor>Strakhov, Elizaveta</editor><editor role="translator">Strakhov, Elizaveta</editor><title>John Lydgate's Dance of Death and Related Works</title><imprint>
 <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace><date>2019</date></imprint>
 </monogr>
 </biblStruct>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
  <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s), textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor, congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p><correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on Github: https://github.com/mets-editions/cook-lydgate/blob/main/cook-lydgate-export-corrections-log.docx</p>
        </correction></editorialDecl><schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
 </encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change>Encoded in HTML</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
    <text><body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><anchor xml:id="Cook-Lydgate-18-Three-Messengers-Enotes"/><div type="text">
 <note type="enote" n="1">3<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Job</hi>. Protagonist of the Book of Job in the Old Testament, Job is a paradigmatic figure of human suffering and perseverance. To disprove Satan, who maintains that humans only love God when in good fortune and prosperity, God chooses a wealthy and happy man, Job, and tests his faith by sending him a series of cataclysmic misfortunes. Job loses his livelihood, his family, is afflicted with disease, but, though embittered, ultimately maintains his faith and gains insight into the mysterious and, from the human perspective, arbitrary workings of the divine.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="2">7<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">And seide his lyf nas bote a</hi><hi rend="italic"> breth</hi>. Compare Job 7:7: “Remember that my life is but wind, and my eyes shall not return to see good things.”</note>
 <note type="enote" n="3">10<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">For his righte wol he not lete</hi>. The subject of this line is Death.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="4">45<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">dedly synne</hi>. The Christian church recognizes two classes of sin: venial and mortal. Venial sins are a violation of the moral law that merit punishment on earth but do not break the covenant with God, although their repeated occurrence may predispose one to graver infractions. Mortal sins break the covenant with God through a severe violation of Christian precepts and, without full repentance and divine forgiveness, ratified through the Church, result in eternal exclusion from the kingdom of Heaven.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="5">46<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">veyghe</hi>. An alternate spelling of ME <hi rend="italic">weien</hi>, this word literally means, according to the <hi rend="italic">MED</hi>, “To weigh (somebody, a soul, one’s deeds, etc. in or as in a balance) to determine worthiness of divine punishment or reward, damnation or salvation; weigh (the soul) on the divine balance at the Day of Judgment” (sense 1b(a)).</note>
 <note type="enote" n="6">47<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">ginne</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Ginne</hi> has the same wide semantic field as the French <hi rend="italic">engin</hi>: thus, according to the <hi rend="italic">MED</hi>: “Inventive talent, ingenuity, cleverness; an expedient, scheme; strategy; trickery, treachery; ruse, wile; an ingenious device or contrivance, machine; an instrument; a machine or structure used in assaulting or defending fortifications, a siege machine or tower.” The semantic breadth of the word lends richness to the characterization of Aventures.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="7">53<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Seint Poul bit we schulden awake</hi>. An allusion to 1 Thessalonians 5:6: “Therefore, let us not sleep, as others do; but let us watch, and be sober.”</note>
 <note type="enote" n="8">68<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hende</hi>. Literally “handsy,” the same adjective applied to Nicholas in Chaucer’s Miller’s Tale. See <hi rend="italic">CT</hi> I (A) 3199.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="9">100<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">hosel</hi>. The Eucharist is a Christian rite that goes back to the biblical New Testament, when Jesus instructed His followers during the Last Supper, on the night before His Crucifixion, to eat bread and drink wine in remembrance of His body and blood. Still practiced today, the rite consists of parishioners imbibing wine and bread blessed by a priest at the conclusion of a church service.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="10"><space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Bereveth</hi><hi rend="italic"> hem bothe hosel and schrift</hi>. The consequence of dying without repenting and receiving forgiveness for mortal sin is, according to the Christian church, eternal damnation. Compare <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 45</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="11">105<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">ure</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lordes kniht</hi>. This phrase is apposite to <hi rend="italic">Seynt Poul</hi>. On St. Paul’s illness, compare 2 Corinthians 12:1–10 and Galatians 4:12–14.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="12">141–44<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Wher ben heo . . . uppon heore steeden</hi>. This passage represents a well-known medieval motif known as <hi rend="italic">ubi sunt</hi>, a lament for the death of revered figures from the past and for the inexorable passage of time that draws us, in the present, further from an imagined Golden Age. The convention of using the Latin phrase <hi rend="italic">ubi sunt</hi> (meaning “where are they?”) goes back to an early use of the motif in the Book of Baruch 3:16–19. Modern readers may recognize the well-known phrase “But where are the snows of yester-year?” as exemplifying this motif; the phrase comes from Dante Gabriel Rossetti’s 1870 translation of the medieval French poet François Villon’s <hi rend="italic">Ballade des dames du temps </hi><hi rend="italic">jadis</hi> (1461). In addition to invoking the general <hi rend="italic">ubi sunt</hi> motif, this stanza in “Three Messengers of Death” (DIMEV 5387) is a textual allusion to the <hi rend="italic">Sayings of Saint Bernard</hi>, a popular Middle English poem composed c. 1275: see Furnivall’s edition of the <hi rend="italic">Sayings</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Minor Poems</hi>, pp. 511–22, especially lines 181–86 (p. 521).</note>
 <note type="enote" n="13">163<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Me may reche the helewowe</hi>. Surely there is wordplay here on <hi rend="italic">helewough</hi> (end wall of building), continuing the architectural motif earlier in the stanza, and <hi rend="italic">hell woe</hi>, or the suffering found in hell.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="14">172<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">him</hi>. The antecedent of “him” is Death in line 160.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="15">180<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">that is wormes mete</hi>. Proverbial. See Whiting W675.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="16">186<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Matussal</hi><hi rend="italic">é</hi>. Methuselah is mentioned in Genesis 5:21–27 as the longest-living person in the Hebrew Bible, dying at the age of 969 years old; he is also an important member of the genealogy connecting Adam and Noah, as the son of Enoch and father of Lamech. His name also comes up in passing in 1 Chronicles 1:3 and Luke 3:37.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="17">191<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">prime</hi>. This indication of time refers to one of the set times for prayer, by which Christian clergy structure their day; this practice is known as the Liturgy of the Hours, the Divine Office, or the canonical hours.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="18">194<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">seynt </hi><hi rend="italic">Austyn</hi>. St. Augustine of Hippo (354–430 CE) was a Christian theologian and church father (that is, a founding figure for Christian thought) living in a Roman province of Northern Africa, where he served as bishop of Hippo Regius. His writings, such as <hi rend="italic">The City of God</hi>, <hi rend="italic">On Christian Doctrine</hi> and his autobiographical <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>, have been enormous influences on the development of the Western theological and philosophical traditions. The author seems to be invoking Augustine in this moment to lend his words additional authority.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="19">208<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Ne scholden him of pyne bringe</hi>. The antecedent of “him” in this line is the man in line 201.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="20">222<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Trinité</hi>. The Christian doctrine of the Trinity holds that the Christian God is one God in three coequal and coeternal manifestations that are distinct from one another but of one substance: the Father, the Son (Jesus Christ), and the Holy Ghost. A useful popular comparison is to consider the physical properties of water, whereby ice, water, and vapor are three different manifestations of the same substance.</note>
 </div></body></text></TEI>
