<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0" xml:id="Cook-Lydgate-10-Lansdowne-Enotes-tei">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt><title>Explanatory Notes to Dance of Death: B Version (Lansdowne)</title><author>Cook, Megan L.</author><author>Strakhov, Elizaveta</author><sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
 <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
 <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
 <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
 <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder><respStmt><persName>Conklin, Ashley R.</persName><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-08">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-08">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-08">Entered corrections for print edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName><resp from="2023-02" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName><resp from="2024-02" to="2024-02">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Norris, James</persName><resp from="2024-03" to="2024-05">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Reviewed and suggested explanatory notes</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp><resp from="2018-06" to="2018-07">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Price, Eleanor</persName><resp from="2024-03" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2023-11" to="2023-11">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Entered corrections for print edition</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Formatted for print edition</resp><resp from="2023-02" to="2023-11">Formatted for XML export</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Yee, Pamela M.</persName><resp from="2018-07" to="2024-01">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp>Collated and entered corrections</resp><resp from="2023-11" to="2023-11">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2018-07" to="2018-09">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Encoded in TEI in 2024</edition>
 </editionStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
 <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <availability status="restricted">
 <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
 </availability>
    <date/>
 </publicationStmt><seriesStmt>
 <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title><respStmt><persName>Ralph Arbelo</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Mead Bowen</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Katherine Briant</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Theresa Coletti</persName><orgName>University of Maryland</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Ashley R. Conklin</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Rita Copeland</persName><orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Steffi Delcourt</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Joe Easterly</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Susanna Fein</persName><orgName>Kent State University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Sue Gleason</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>David A. Lawton</persName><orgName>Washington University in St. Louis</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Michael Livingston</persName><orgName>The Citadel</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Alan Lupack</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Andrea Noto</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Katie Papas</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Section Supervisor, The Robbins Library, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Russell A. Peck</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Eve Salisbury</persName><orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Nathan Sarr</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Techincal Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>R. A. Shoaf</persName><orgName>University of Florida</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Lynn Staley</persName><orgName>Colgate University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName><orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Pamela M. Yee</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt></seriesStmt>    
 <sourceDesc>
 <biblStruct>
 <monogr><author>Lydgate, John</author><author>Unknown</author><editor>Cook, Megan L.</editor><editor>Strakhov, Elizaveta</editor><editor role="translator">Strakhov, Elizaveta</editor><title>John Lydgate's Dance of Death and Related Works</title><imprint>
 <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace><date>2019</date></imprint>
 </monogr>
 </biblStruct>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
  <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s), textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor, congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p><correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on Github: https://github.com/mets-editions/cook-lydgate/blob/main/cook-lydgate-export-corrections-log.docx</p>
        </correction></editorialDecl><schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
 </encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language></langUsage></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change>Encoded in HTML</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
    <text><body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><anchor xml:id="Cook-Lydgate-10-Lansdowne-Enotes"/><div type="text">
 <note type="enote" n="1">Before 1<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Incipit Macrobius</hi>. Three manuscripts of the B version of the poem (Lansdowne, Lincoln, and Leiden) include an attribution to Macrobius at the beginning of the poem, probably a misunderstanding or corruption of “Macabre” (the note in Leiden is in a later hand). Macrobius Ambrosius Theodosius was a fifth-century Roman author whose <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Dream of Scipio</hi>, a treatise on the interpretation of dreams, was widely read in the Middle Ages; the ascription to Macrobius might also represent an attempt to associate the text with a known textual authority rather than the more mysterious “Macabre” (see <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">Introduction, pp. 4–6</ref>). Two other manuscripts of the B version (Bodleian and Corpus Christi) identify it in their incipits as the “Dance of Pauls,” referring to the murals painted in the Pardon Churchyard of St. Paul’s Cathedral in London. None of the A text manuscripts include references to either Macrobius or the St. Paul’s location.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="2">Before 9<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Angelus</hi>. The French <hi rend="italic">Danse</hi> concludes, in some manuscripts, with a Latin stanza rubricated as “Angelus et doctor locuntur” (The Angel and the doctor speak) at line 543. Marchant’s edition opens and closes with woodcuts showing an angel hovering over an author figure (identifiable by his pose of reading at a lectern); this angel is holding scrolls containing the Latin texts that open and close the French work. If an angel was included at the beginning of the Parisian mural, it could explain the B version’s decision to give the second stanza to this character, who does not otherwise speak in the poem.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="3">9<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">this myrrour</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 49</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="4">19<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">And lik to Petir have </hi><hi rend="italic">the sovereynté</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 59</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="5">35<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Ye must forsake of gold your appill round</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 75</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="6">45<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">A symple shete — ther is no more to seyn —</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 85</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="7">54<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Your hatt of red</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 94</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="8">Before 65<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Imperatrix</hi>. This is a new character, who does not appear in the original French <hi rend="italic">Danse </hi><hi rend="italic">macabre</hi> or in the A version.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="9">77<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Deth seith chekmat</hi>. The concept of a match of chess or a similar game played against Death or another supranatural figure is an ancient one. W. L. Nash writes, “[t]he ancient Egyptian game, which we call the game of draughts, has been the subject of many myths and legends. Plato quotes an ancient tradition that the game was invented by Thoth. Herodotus (II, 122) repeats the legend related to him by the Egyptian priests, that Rhampsinitus (Rameses III) descended into the lower world, there played at draughts with Isis, and returned, a victor, to Earth. Plutarch (de Isis, 12), probably referring to the same legend, says that Hermes (Thoth) played at draughts with the moon, and won five lunar days, which he added to the solar year” (341). In Chaucer’s <hi rend="italic">Book</hi><hi rend="italic"> of the Duchess</hi>, the Man in Black, lamenting his love, states that “fals Fortune hath pleyd a game / Atte ches with me” (lines 618–19). Several examples survive in visual art, most notably a large painting of a man playing chess with Death in Täby Church outside of Stockholm, painted by Albertus Pictor c. 1480–90, which is said to have inspired the similar scene in Ingmar Bergman’s 1957 film <hi rend="italic">The Seventh Seal</hi>.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="10">81<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Sir Patriarch, ful sad and humble</hi><hi rend="italic"> of cheere</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 121</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="11">83<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Your dowble cros</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 123</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="12">Before 129<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Princeps</hi>. In A (line 145), this speaker is identified as the Constable.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="13">131<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Carlemayn</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 139</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="14">132–33<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">worthy Arthour of . . . the Rounde Table</hi>. A central figure in medieval romance, King Arthur was a legendary ruler of England who was also understood as a historical figure in the later Middle Ages due to his central role in works like Geoffrey of Monmouth’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Kings</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Britain</hi> (c. 1136). Arthur was said to have gathered the knights in his service around a round table at his court at Camelot, which served as their base in their search for the Holy Grail, the chalice used by Jesus at the Last Supper. Many of the Knights of the Round Table, including Lancelot, Galahad, and Gawain, appear as the protagonists of their own romance narratives.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="15">151<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">brouht </hi><hi rend="italic">to lure</hi>. The phrase is used in hawking to mean “to bring somebody under control” (<hi rend="italic">MED lure</hi> [n.1], sense 1c).</note>
 <note type="enote" n="16">Before 161<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Comes et Baro</hi>. In A (line 177), this speaker is identified as “the Baroun or the Knyht.”</note>
 <note type="enote" n="17">Before 177<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Abbas et prior</hi>. In A (line 223), this speaker is identified only as the Abbot. B adds the Prior.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="18">188<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">somwhat the lesse grevaunce</hi>. In A, this line reads “passinge grete grevaunce” (line 244), a somewhat stronger statement of dismay than the revised line.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="19">Before 193<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Abbatissa</hi>. This is a new character, who does not appear in the original French <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi>; she corresponds to the A version’s Abbesse (line 249).</note>
 <note type="enote" n="20">Before 209<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Iudex</hi>. This is a new character, who does not appear in the original French <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi> or in the A version.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="21">216<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Weel is</hi><hi rend="italic"> hym that alwey weel doth</hi>. Proverbial. See Whiting D278.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="22">225<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Doctour of Canon and Cyvile</hi>. In medieval Europe, two legal systems operated alongside one another: canon law, which was made and enforced by ecclesiastical authorities and used throughout Europe, and civil law, which was made and enforced by local secular authorities. Medieval universities taught both systems of law; the doctor whom Death addresses in this stanza is a scholar of both, as indicated by his terminal degree (<hi rend="italic">doctor utrisque juris</hi>). This is a new character, who does not appear in the original French <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi> or in the A version.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="23">235<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">No man of his liff hath charter nor seele</hi>. A charter is a formal document granting certain rights or privileges; a seal attached to such a document would give it legal effect. Using legal language, Death asserts here that no one has authority over his or her own life.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="24">Before 241<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Miles et armiger</hi>. In A, both the speaker marker and line 217 name only the Squire. B adds the Knight.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="25">Before 257<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Maior</hi>. This is a new character, who does not appear in the original French <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi> or in the A version.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="26">273<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Sir Chanon Reguler</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">MED</hi> (<hi rend="italic">canoun</hi> [n.2], sense 2a) defines a canon regular as “a canon living under a quasimonastic rule, a regular canon, an Augustinian or a Premonstratensian canon.” Such canons would have lived on the grounds of St. Paul’s during the time the <hi rend="italic">Dance of Death</hi> was present in the Pardon Churchyard. This is a new character, who does not appear in the original French <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi> or in the A version.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="27">289<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Sir Dean or Chanon, with many gret</hi><hi rend="italic"> prebend</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 313</ref> above. The B version adds the reference to a dean, the head of a chapter of canons associated with a cathedral or collegiate church (<hi rend="italic">MED den</hi> [n.2]), which would be particularly appropriate for the <hi rend="italic">Dance of Death</hi>’s setting at St. Paul’s.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="28">297<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">My divers cures, my riche </hi><hi rend="italic">personages —</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 321</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="29">305<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">ye be barbid and claad in clothis blaake</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 377</ref> above. Although the Monk appears in both the French <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi> and the A version, his stanzas here are substantially revised.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="30">306<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Chastly receyved the mantil and the ryng</hi>. The mantle (a sleeveless overgarment worn by monks and nuns) and the ring were outward symbols of a vow of perpetual chastity typically bestowed by a bishop.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="31">323<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Sir Chartreux</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 347</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="32">337<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Sir Sergeant</hi>. The Sergeant-at-Law is equivalent to the Man of Law in the A version of the text (lines 465–80) and is distinct from the Sergeant who appears in the B text from lines 401–16.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="33">348–49<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Tescape awey from . . . nor gret prudence</hi>. In A (lines 476–77), these lines appear in the opposite order.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="34">Before 353<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Generosa</hi>. This is a new character, who does not appear in the original French <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi>, but her exchange with Death corresponds to the A version’s Gentilwomman Amerous (line 449).</note>
 <note type="enote" n="35">355<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">As fair as ye was whilom </hi><hi rend="italic">Polliceene</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 451</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="36">356<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Penolope and the queen Eleyn</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 452</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="37">357<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Yit on this daunce </hi><hi rend="italic">thei went bothe tweyn</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 453</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="38">376<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">And alle shul deie for an </hi><hi rend="italic">appyll rounde</hi>. See A version’s<ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal"> note to line 288</ref> above. A similar image appears in line 35, in the description of the Emperor.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="39">401<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">thou Sergeant with thi stately </hi><hi rend="italic">maas</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 361</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="40">414<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">And may nat flee, thouh I hadde it sworn</hi>. See A version’s<ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal"> note to line 374</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="41">417<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Maister Jurour</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to before line 481</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="42">433<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Gentil menstral</hi>. Although the Minstrel appears in the A version (line 497), his stanzas here are substantially revised.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="43">440<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Bettir late than nevyr</hi>. Proverbial. See Whiting L89.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="44">448<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">alle be nat mery that othirwhyle daunce</hi>. Proverbial. See Whiting A88.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="45">Before 449<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Famulus</hi>. This is a new character, who does not appear in the original French <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi> or in the A version.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="46">456<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">the tyde abidith no </hi><hi rend="italic">man</hi>. Proverbial. See Whiting T318.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="47">465–66<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">that loken so fast / </hi><hi rend="italic">In othir mennys watris what thei eyle</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to lines 417–18 </ref>above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="48">472<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">al men shal repe as thei have sowe</hi>. Proverbial. See Whiting S542.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="49">465–80<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Ye phisiciens . . . fynaly no </hi><hi rend="italic">boote</hi>. Death’s dialogue with the Physician in B seems closer to the French <hi rend="italic">Danse</hi> (lines 351–66) than the corresponding section in A (lines 417–32). Where the <hi rend="italic">Danse</hi> reads: “Comme aultre vous convient mourir” (line 356: You must die like any other), the A version omits this, while the B version has: “For Deth comyng sodeynly doth assaile / As weel lechis as othir” (lines 469–70). Similarly, only B reproduces the <hi rend="italic">Danse</hi>’s “Plus n’y vault herbe, ne racine, / N’autre remede” (lines 364–65: “Plants and roots and other remedies / Are no longer any good”) with “Wherfore shal helpe nothir herbe nor roote, / Nor no medycine . . .” (lines 478–79), while the A version omits the line. It is not clear why Lydgate may have gone back to his French source in revising this specific section.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="50">480<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">For ageyns Deth is fynaly no boote</hi>. Proverbial. See Whiting D78.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="51">Before 497<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Artifex</hi>. This is a new character, who does not appear in the original French <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi> or in the A version.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="52">509–12<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">She pershith sheeldis . . . be no </hi><hi rend="italic">deffence</hi>. In this passage, Death is referred to as feminine. In French, Death is feminine (<hi rend="italic">la mort</hi>), but there is no section that corresponds to the Artifex stanzas in the <hi rend="italic">Danse macabre</hi>.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="53">544<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">For as sone deieth a yong sheep </hi><hi rend="italic">as an olde</hi>. The usage of “sheep” here is metaphorical; see A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 543</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="54">545<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Ye that have lived long in wildirnesse</hi>. See A version’s <ref target="insert-internal-link" type="internal">note to line 609</ref> above.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="55">552<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">this liff heer </hi><hi rend="italic">is but a pylgrymage</hi>. The idea of a life as a pilgrimage is present in a variety of late medieval devotional texts, perhaps most notably in Guillaume de Deguileville’s <hi rend="italic">Le pèlerinage de la vie humaine</hi>, which was translated twice into Middle English, once in prose as <hi rend="italic">The Pilgrimage </hi><hi rend="italic">of the Life of the Manhood</hi> (dated to the 1420s) and once in verse as <hi rend="italic">The Pilgrimage of the Life</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Man</hi> (1426/27); the latter text is attributed to Lydgate, although the attribution remains questionable. Compare also Chaucer’s Knight’s Tale: “This world nys but a thurghfare ful of wo, / And we been pilgrymes, passynge to and fro. / Deeth is an ende of every worldly soore” (<hi rend="italic">CT</hi> I[A] 2847–49). See also Whiting P201.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="56">561<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">Ye folk that </hi><hi rend="italic">loken upon this scripture</hi>. “Scripture” seems to refer specifically to the written word; the A text uses “portrature,” a word with visual connotations, in the equivalent passage at line 633.</note>
 <note type="enote" n="57">569–70<space rend="indent1"/><hi rend="italic">What is mannys liff but . . . a puff of wynde</hi>. See James 4:15. See also Whiting L242.</note>
 </div></body></text></TEI>
